<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Loyalty protesting against popery, and phanaticism popishly affected being a sermon preached on the fifth of November, 1682 at St. Olave's Hartstreet, London / by William Wray ...</title>
            <author>Wray, William, 1650?-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A71287</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12946</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12738599</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12738599</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93057</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A71287)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93057)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 995:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Loyalty protesting against popery, and phanaticism popishly affected being a sermon preached on the fifth of November, 1682 at St. Olave's Hartstreet, London / by William Wray ...</title>
                  <author>Wray, William, 1650?-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93057:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93057:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Loyalty Proteſting againſt Popery,</hi> AND <hi>Phanaticiſm Popiſhly Affected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEING A SERMON Preached on the Fifth of <hi>NOVEMBER,</hi> 1682. At St. <hi>Olave's Hartſtreet,</hi> London.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM WRAY,</hi> M. A. Chaplain to the Right Honourable <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkley</hi> Baron of <hi>Stratton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:93057:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93057:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached <hi>November</hi> V. 1682.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>GEN. XLIX. 6.</bibl> O my Soul, come not thou into their Secret; unto their Aſſembly, mine Honour, be not thou united.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>The whole Paragraph.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver. 5.</hi>
                     </bibl> 
                     <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> are Brethren: Inſtruments of cruelty are in their Habitations.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver. 6.</hi>
                     </bibl> O my Soul, come not thou into their Secret; unto their Aſſembly, mine Honour, be not thou united: for in their Anger they ſlew a man, and in their ſelf-will they digged down a wall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver. 7.</hi>
                     </bibl> Curſed be their Anger, for it was fierce; and their Wrath, for it was cruel; I will divide them in <hi>Jacob,</hi> and ſcatter them in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS Chapter contains the ſum of <hi>Jacobs</hi> dying Prophecies, concerning the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of his Sons, in after-times; how they ſhould be the Heads of Tribes, what the Lots of their Poſterity ſhould be, and what <hi>eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Remarkable</hi> ſhould betide each of them, in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93057:3"/> the Land of <hi>Promiſe.</hi> And theſe are call'd <hi>Jacobs</hi> Bleſſings, <hi>wherewith he</hi> bleſſed <hi>every one of them.—v.</hi> 28. But we muſt take the <hi>Term</hi> in a very <hi>lax</hi> ſenſe, if we reckon <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi>'s ſentence here in the Text, into the Number of <hi>Bleſſings:</hi> which is a ſmart <hi>Reprimand</hi> in the beginning, and a downright <hi>Curſe</hi> in the cloſe. To which we may either anſwer, that they are <hi>Bleſſings</hi> in the <hi>General,</hi> and that one <hi>Exception</hi> ſhould not invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date the <hi>Rule:</hi> or that the Original <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies either to <hi>Bleſs</hi> or <hi>Curſe,</hi> and that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is here a<note place="margin">Job 2. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Genus</hi> and includes both: or laſtly, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy is <hi>ambiguouſly</hi> delivered; and what in the <hi>Letter</hi> appears a <hi>Judgment,</hi> in the <hi>Accompliſhment</hi> prov'd ſomewhat of a <hi>Bleſſing.</hi> The Menace is, that God ſhould <hi>divide them in</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ſcatter them in</hi> Iſrael, and ſo it came to paſs; For upon the <hi>Dividend,</hi> the <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Simeon</hi> had no particular lot of their <hi>own;</hi> but poſſeſt a Canton of <hi>Judah</hi>'s Portion, the <hi>Over-plus</hi> and <hi>ſpare-part</hi> of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance,<note place="margin">Joſh. 19. 1, 9.</note> which was too large for their <hi>Number,</hi> till the entire Conqueſt of the <hi>Amalekites</hi> in <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi>'s time; and then they enlarged their Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron. 4. ult.</hi>
               </note> by entring into their Poſſeſſions. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the <hi>Jews</hi> report that the <hi>Simeonites</hi> were<note place="margin">Targum Hieroſol.</note> all along a <hi>ſcattered</hi> people; being commonly <hi>Scribes</hi> or <hi>Paedagogues,</hi> and ſo diſperſt among the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93057:3"/> other <hi>Tribes.</hi> And then upon the <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Levi,</hi> the Prophecy was fulfilled <hi>exactly,</hi> though much to their <hi>Advantage.</hi> For <hi>Levi</hi> had <hi>no Part nor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 10. 9.</note> 
               <hi>with his Brethren;</hi> and it was well for him that he had not; for <hi>the Lord was his Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> And his Poſterity being choſen to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Service of God, the Adminiſtration of <hi>Holy things,</hi> they had the <hi>Tenths</hi> of the whole Land, beſide many other <hi>Offerings</hi> and <hi>Perquiſites,</hi> aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them for that <hi>Duty.</hi> But though God was ſo <hi>Merciful</hi> to fulfil the prediction in a <hi>gracious</hi> ſence, eſpecially on <hi>Levi</hi>'s part; yet undoubtedly it was intended by the good old <hi>Patriarch,</hi> as a tart <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof</hi> of thoſe his Sons inhumane <hi>Treachery,</hi> and bloody <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of the <hi>Sichemites;</hi> an account whereof you have at large in the 34. <hi>ch.</hi> which, to eaſe you of trouble, I ſhall here tranſcribe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jacob,</hi> having broke off the Yoke of a <hi>Triple</hi> Apprentiſhip under <hi>Laban</hi> his Father-in-law, was upon his Return unto the <hi>Land of his Kindred,</hi> as<note place="margin">Gen. 31. 13.</note> God had commanded him. And, after ſeveral Adventures, being come ſafe to the deſired <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> he pitch'd his Tent at <hi>Shalem,</hi> and there<note place="margin">ch. 33. 18.</note> bought a piece of ground of <hi>Hamor</hi> the King of the Countrey, whereupon to build an Altar, to offer Sacrifice for his ſafe Arrival there. During their ſtay, <hi>Dinah, Jacobs</hi> daughter, went abroad<note place="margin">ch. 34. 1.</note>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:93057:4"/> to viſit, and acquaint her ſelf with, the <hi>Daughters of the Land,</hi> whom Prince <hi>Shechem</hi> the Son of <hi>Hamor eſpied,</hi> liked, and <hi>deflowered:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſolicited the King his Father, to treat with <hi>Jacob</hi> upon a <hi>Marriage;</hi> which he did, propoſing<note place="margin">Gen. 34. 6.</note> a <hi>free</hi> Correſpondence, that they might <hi>match</hi> into each others Family, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> would take the Country for their <hi>Home,</hi> and ſettle, and get Poſſeſſions in it, and that they might peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably <hi>Dwell</hi> and <hi>Trade</hi> together. <hi>Shechem</hi> back'd<note place="margin">ver. 11.</note> the <hi>King,</hi> proffering them to make their own Demands for a <hi>Dowry,</hi> and that whatſoever <hi>they</hi> would ask, <hi>he</hi> would make it good. The ſons of <hi>Jacob,</hi> that ſtudied rather to be <hi>Reveng'd</hi> than <hi>Reconciled,</hi> diſſembled their <hi>Heart-burning</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments,</hi> by a <hi>half-complyance:</hi> only objecting a <hi>Caſe</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and that they could by no means make <hi>Matches</hi> with them, becauſe they were men of a <hi>different Religion:</hi> but if the <hi>Sichemites</hi> would conſent to be as <hi>They</hi> were, take the Sacrament of <hi>their</hi> Covenant, and every Male of them be <hi>Circumciſed,</hi> as God commanded <hi>Abraham,</hi> they<note place="margin">ch. 17. 10.</note> gave their Faith to agree to their <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> to give their <hi>Daughters</hi> to the <hi>Sichemites,</hi> and take the <hi>Sichemites Daughters</hi> unto <hi>them,</hi> and to <hi>dwell</hi> and become <hi>one people</hi> with them. Theſe <hi>Terms</hi> pleaſed <hi>Hamor,</hi> but the <hi>Prince</hi> eſpecially; who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93057:4"/> was eager to have the <hi>Match</hi> ſucceed upon any <hi>ſcore:</hi> and to ſhew his <hi>zeal,</hi> he deferred not, but took the <hi>Ritual mark</hi> upon him preſently; and the next buſineſs was to perſwade the <hi>People</hi> (after their <hi>Princes</hi> example) to do ſo too: to which end they inſinuated that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were <hi>peaceable good-natured</hi> men, and men of <hi>Fortunes;</hi> that the Land was <hi>large</hi> enough to hold them; that Entertaining them would both enrich and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it; and that the only <hi>condition</hi> they ſtood upon, was a certain <hi>Ceremony,</hi> that every Male among the <hi>Sichemites,</hi> would ſubmit to be <hi>Circumciſed,</hi> as <hi>they</hi> all were. The people being <hi>over-perſwaded,</hi> partly by their <hi>Reaſons,</hi> but more by their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, univerſally conſented, and took the <hi>bloody ſign</hi> (ominouſly <hi>ſo</hi> to <hi>them</hi>) into their <hi>fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus theſe poor <hi>Credulous</hi> Wretches, being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed into the ſnare, and rendred incapable, for the preſent, either to <hi>Fight</hi> or <hi>Flee,</hi> lay at the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of a <hi>Provoked</hi> enemy, <hi>Impotent</hi> and <hi>Defenceleſs;</hi> neither capable of <hi>offending</hi> others, nor ſaving themſelves. <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> took the Advantage of their own <hi>Treaſon</hi> and the <hi>Sichemites folly,</hi> and while they were <hi>ſore,</hi> with each man his Sword in his hand, they came upon the City, and ſlew all their Males, the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> and the whole <hi>Royal line</hi> not excepted: and thus they reſcued
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93057:5"/> their Siſter from her <hi>Raviſher.</hi> And to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh their Revenge, they plundered their <hi>Houſes,</hi> drove off their <hi>Cattle,</hi> and carried their Wives and little ones captive into their own Tent. At the News of which Treacherous and bloody <hi>Doings,</hi> their Father <hi>Jacob</hi> was heartily <hi>aſham'd</hi> and <hi>griev'd;</hi> and could not forbear to let them <hi>know</hi> ſo, ſaying unto <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> theſe <hi>Traitors, Murderers</hi> and <hi>Regicides, Ye have troubled</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 34. 30.</note> 
               <hi>Me, to make Me to ſtink among the Inhabitants of the Land:</hi> Which <hi>Horrid</hi> ſtory he could never <hi>forget,</hi> nor be <hi>reconciled</hi> to, to his <hi>dying day.</hi> Simeon <hi>and</hi> Levi <hi>are Brethren: Inſtruments of cruelty are in their Habitations. O my ſoul, come not thou into their ſecret; unto their Aſſembly, mine honor, be not thou united.—Curſed be their Anger, for it was fierce; and their Wrath, for it was cruel.</hi> Theſe were his <hi>laſt</hi> thoughts, his <hi>Death-bed</hi> Remembrance, of that Days work. And indeed there are ſo many Circumſtances, both <hi>baſe</hi> and <hi>bloody,</hi> attending it, as render it moſt <hi>diſhonourably</hi> and <hi>barbarouſly</hi> wicked. In ſumming up whereof, give me leave to draw a <hi>Parallel,</hi> ſo far as it will reach, between the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy</hi> of the <hi>Text</hi> and <hi>that</hi> of the Day.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs the <hi>ſtory</hi> is too <hi>modeſt</hi> for the <hi>Occaſion;</hi> but who can help it, ſince there's ſcarce any <hi>Age,</hi> any <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> either <hi>Sacred</hi> or <hi>prophane,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:93057:5"/> that will afford a <hi>Match</hi> for it? But to bring the Inſtances as near together as we can,</p>
            <p>1. Let us compare the Circumſtances of the <hi>Perſons,</hi> the <hi>Conſpirators,</hi> on both ſides.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> were <hi>Hamors gueſts,</hi> though not his <hi>Subjects;</hi> being admitted upon <hi>Courteſie</hi> to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ in thoſe Quarters: and it was very ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully done to violate the Laws of <hi>Hoſpitality,</hi> and fall foul upon <hi>him</hi> that had ſo <hi>befriended</hi> them. The <hi>Provocation</hi> indeed was <hi>great,</hi> and almoſt <hi>invincible;</hi> though it appeared to have been rather a Matter of <hi>Infirmity</hi> than <hi>Deſign:</hi> the offender offering all the <hi>Reſtitution</hi> that could be, either for the <hi>Damſels</hi> Honour or his <hi>own.</hi> And if this was not ſufficient to make them <hi>Friends,</hi> they ſhould, for theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, have been generous <hi>enemies</hi> at the leaſt. Thus ſtood the caſe with the Conſpirators in the Text.</p>
            <p>But for thoſe of the Day, they had the Bonds of <hi>Nature</hi> upon them as well as <hi>Gratitude:</hi> They were <hi>Natives</hi> and <hi>Subjects,</hi> and the Kings of <hi>England</hi> their Nurſing Parents, under whoſe benign Beams they drew their firſt Breath; at whoſe <hi>Care</hi> they were brought up ſecure from the hands of (ſuch as <hi>themſelves) Blood-thirſty</hi> and <hi>Cruel</hi> men, and by vertue of <hi>Their</hi> Laws, <hi>eſtated</hi> and <hi>confirmed</hi> in their juſt Rights and Inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Thus they did eat their Bread at the charge
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93057:6"/> of the <hi>Government, That</hi> was their <hi>Protection,</hi> and they ſate ſafe under their own <hi>Vines,</hi> and under their own <hi>Figg-trees.</hi> But that's not all.</p>
            <p>They did not only enjoy the Influence of a <hi>Royal Providence, in Common</hi> with other Subjects, but had the Advantage of <hi>ſingular</hi> kindneſſes, which, ſuch as deſerved <hi>better,</hi> neither did, nor were capable of receiving. Legal Mulcts were taken off, and all arrears remitted, that they were behind hand for their <hi>obſtinacy</hi> and <hi>diſobedience</hi> in the foregoing <hi>Reign.</hi> They were admitted to <hi>Court,</hi> taken into <hi>Favour,</hi> employed in <hi>Truſts</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> and prefer'd to <hi>Honours,</hi> as if they had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther been men of <hi>Merit,</hi> than <hi>Law-breakers</hi> and Malefactors. Theſe were the <hi>Simeonites,</hi> the <hi>Lay-Conſpirators</hi> of this <hi>Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for the Sons of <hi>Levi,</hi> they were <hi>Tenants</hi> at <hi>Will</hi> to the Government for their <hi>Lives.</hi> There were <hi>Sanguinary</hi> Laws in force againſt them, and every hour they lived, was upon <hi>Mercy</hi> and by <hi>Permisſion.</hi> And yet from the <hi>firſt</hi> of that Kings Reign, to the <hi>happy Diſcovery,</hi> here they <hi>lived,</hi> here they had their <hi>Freedom,</hi> here they enjoyed the benefit of the <hi>Law,</hi> and (though all their Lives were forfeited) not one of them felt the <hi>ſmart</hi> of it. That if <hi>Suſpenſion</hi> of the <hi>Laws,</hi> if <hi>Remisſion</hi> of <hi>penalties,</hi> if <hi>pardon</hi> of <hi>unrepented faults,</hi> if <hi>Reward</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:93057:6"/> above and without <hi>Merit</hi> be Princely favours, and ſuch as double the Subjects <hi>natural</hi> obligations to Obedience and Loyalty; then <hi>theſe</hi> were the Men, equal to any in the world, that ſtood ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for theſe engagements; for there were none of them that were not beholden to the King, either for their <hi>Lives,</hi> their <hi>Fortunes,</hi> their <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> or <hi>undeſerved Courteſies</hi> and <hi>preferments;</hi> and many of them were engaged for <hi>all.</hi> And yet theſe <hi>unthankful</hi> Miſcreants conſpired againſt their King, their <hi>Friend</hi> and <hi>Benefactor,</hi> and ſought <hi>his Life</hi> to whom, in more than <hi>one</hi> reſpect, they ow'd their <hi>own.</hi> Neither could they, with the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> pretend any <hi>Provocation,</hi> of <hi>weight</hi> enough to turn the ſcale ſo beladen with <hi>good turns,</hi> or ſo much as give a juſt occaſion of <hi>offence</hi> upon the even <hi>ſquare,</hi> all conſiderations of <hi>Royal favours</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid aſide. Here was no <hi>deflowred Virgin</hi> in the caſe, but the contrary; and all that could be pretended was, that <hi>Spiritual Whoredom</hi> was not <hi>tolerated,</hi> nor <hi>Religion</hi> made a <hi>Proſtitute</hi> to the <hi>Luſt</hi> and <hi>Wantonneſs</hi> of Men.</p>
            <p>2. That which Blackened the faces of the ſons of <hi>Jacob,</hi> was their <hi>Falſhood</hi> and <hi>Treachery.</hi> The <hi>Buſineſs</hi> was made up, the <hi>Terms</hi> agreed, the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions</hi> on the <hi>Sichemites</hi> part <hi>performed,</hi> and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Rite of <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was made the <hi>Sacrament</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:93057:7"/> of this Civil Contract. But contrary to the <hi>Faith</hi> of their <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Promiſe,</hi> contrary to the <hi>Articles</hi> of the <hi>League, Sacred</hi> to all the World; they violate the <hi>Covenant,</hi> break the <hi>Alliance,</hi> and Murder <hi>Thoſe</hi> whom they had bound themſelves to <hi>defend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Obligation</hi> of every Subject to be True to his <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> is no whit inferiour to the moſt <hi>Solemn Contract,</hi> whether he take the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy</hi> or no? 'Tis that which <hi>Nature</hi> and the Bonds of <hi>Society</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige him to: 'Tis that which every <hi>Chriſtian</hi> has ſolemnly <hi>Sworn</hi> in his <hi>Matriculation</hi> Oath, to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Devil and all his works:</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> that <hi>Arch-Conſpirator</hi> againſt the Throne of God: and <hi>all his works of Darkneſs;</hi> and certainly Treaſon and Rebellion have a prime place in that black Catalogue, in ſpight of an <note n="*" place="margin">Index ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius.</note> 
               <hi>Italian ſpunge.</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther branch of that <hi>Initiation</hi> Oath, is, to <hi>keep Gods holy Will and Commandments;</hi> And <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother,</hi> ſtand in the Front of the Second Table. That to <hi>Plot</hi> and <hi>Rebel,</hi> is actually to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce our <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and to abjure <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> as well as Civil <hi>Allegiance,</hi> in two main <hi>Articles</hi> of that Covenant.</p>
            <p>And indeed, other <hi>Oaths</hi> from <hi>Subjects</hi> to their <hi>Prince,</hi> would be very <hi>impertinent,</hi> if either
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93057:7"/> the <hi>Law of Nature</hi> or <hi>Religion</hi> would hold us: they <hi>being</hi> more proper Ligaments of mutual <hi>Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> and <hi>correſpondence</hi> between <hi>Equals</hi> or <hi>ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> and where there is no ſuch <hi>Relative</hi> duty <hi>naturally</hi> owing. That there's as much <hi>Perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> in <hi>Diſloyalty,</hi> though we have never been put to an <hi>Oath,</hi> as if we had ſworn a <hi>Thouſand;</hi> For the <hi>Oath</hi> makes not <hi>that</hi> a Duty which was not <hi>ſo</hi> before, but only ſerves to convince him that takes it, and make him ſenſible that it is ſo, and the more <hi>conſcientious</hi> to perform it. So that the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> of <hi>this Day</hi> were no leſs <hi>Perfidious</hi> than <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> no not <hi>they</hi> who never took the <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Principle of <hi>their</hi> Religion not to take them.</p>
            <p>But here's not only the <hi>Breach</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for, but <hi>Clandeſtine Treachery.</hi> They ſurpriſed their <hi>Allies</hi> and <hi>Confidents</hi> unawares; and having betrayed them into a ſtate of <hi>Impotence</hi> and <hi>Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> murder'd both the <hi>helpleſs,</hi> and <hi>thoſe that were at</hi> Peace <hi>with them. Joſephus</hi> informs us farther,<note place="margin">De Antiq. Jud. l. 1. c. 19.</note> that it was at a time of extraordinary <hi>Feſtivity,</hi> and probably upon the Occaſion of this new <hi>Alliance;</hi> that it was in the <hi>Night</hi> too, when all <hi>Jealouſies</hi> were <hi>huſh'd,</hi> and when weary of the Pleaſures of the Day, the <hi>Sichemites</hi> had <hi>fearleſly</hi> given them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93057:8"/> up to a profound Repoſe: ſo eſſential is it to <hi>Treaſon,</hi> not only to be <hi>Falſe,</hi> but <hi>Cowardly</hi> and <hi>Baſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have hated the ſins of unfaithfulneſs,</hi> ſays the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Bluntly</hi> and <hi>Pathetically:</hi> and certainly there is no ſin ſo deteſtable as <hi>Treachery</hi> is, nor any ſinner in all the Sacred Hiſtory, that hath the like infamous <hi>brand</hi> upon his Memory, as <hi>Judas</hi> hath, who <hi>kiſs'd</hi> and <hi>Betray'd</hi> his Maſter: to whom that of our Saviour was no leſs <hi>ſevere</hi> than <hi>kind, Friend wherefore art thou come?</hi> Which is very applicable to the Occaſion: for, Lord, who ſuſpected our <hi>Roman Judas's?</hi> who had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured them? who had provoked them? or who was at <hi>Enmity</hi> with them? nothing but the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge of their <hi>Principles,</hi> and the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their former <hi>Villanies,</hi> (could at ſuch a <hi>time,</hi> under ſo <hi>gracious</hi> a Prince, of ſo <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>gentle</hi> a Diſpoſition, and ſo particularly <hi>kind</hi> to <hi>them</hi>) have perſwaded any ſober Man, to <hi>ſuſpect</hi> them beforehand, or to <hi>believe</hi> them Traitors when <hi>diſcovered;</hi> ſuch Reaſon had the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from its own <hi>tenderneſs</hi> and <hi>indulgence</hi> toward them, to be <hi>ſecure,</hi> and <hi>hope well</hi> of them. But this is the Time for ſuch Devils to do their work in, according to the example of their <hi>Maſter;</hi> who ſowes his <hi>Tares</hi> in the <hi>Field,</hi> and ſends his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93057:8"/> 
               <hi>Firebrands</hi> into the <hi>Harveſt,</hi> when men <hi>ſleep</hi> and think no harm: and 'tis his <hi>Principle</hi> and <hi>Temper</hi> to Damn and confound <hi>thoſe</hi> that are moſt his <hi>Friends.</hi> That this <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> was <hi>Night-work,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived in an Abyſs of <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> managed in the bowels of the <hi>Earth,</hi> carried on with all the Arts of <hi>ſecrecy,</hi> and that it was circumſtantiated with all the <hi>Formalities</hi> of a Curſed <hi>Treaſon,</hi> I need not tell you, for the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> is no leſs <hi>notorious</hi> now, than the <hi>Plot</hi> was once a <hi>ſecret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Theſe Sons of <hi>Jacob,</hi> to put a good <hi>Face</hi> upon the Matter and prevent ſuſpicion, pretend Religion and a point of Conſcience; that they could not converſe freely with the <hi>Sichemites,</hi> till they were <hi>Circumciſed;</hi> when, in truth, they could not conveniently <hi>Murder</hi> them till <hi>then.</hi> And who could have miſtruſted theſe men of <hi>Perjury,</hi> that had ſuch <hi>tender Conſciences?</hi> who could have imagined but that they were <hi>Saints</hi> in their <hi>Morals,</hi> that were ſo ſcrupulous about a <hi>Ceremony?</hi> Nay, but who would think that the <hi>Sons</hi> of the <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch</hi> ſhould prophane the Sacramental <hi>Badge</hi> of their <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> the <hi>Seal</hi> of the <hi>Promiſes,</hi> the moſt Sacred <hi>Rite</hi> of the Religion of that Age, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſly pervert it to the ends of <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Bloodſhed,</hi> and by the ſame <hi>Symbol</hi> adopt the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemites</hi> into their <hi>Fraternity,</hi> and mark them out
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93057:9"/> for <hi>Murder?</hi> I believe the ſtratagem was a <hi>Novel</hi> in that <hi>Age,</hi> though it be grown <hi>ſtale</hi> in <hi>ours.</hi> No man now almoſt has a deſign to drive, but <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> are of the <hi>Plot.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>Procurers</hi> to our <hi>Luſts,</hi> and <hi>Factors</hi> for our <hi>Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and <hi>Suborners</hi> of a <hi>Poll</hi> when we have a mind to be <hi>Popular.</hi> We defraud or belie our <hi>Brethren</hi> and forſwear our <hi>ſelves;</hi> We clamour the <hi>Church</hi> and ſlander the <hi>Government;</hi> we ſpeak evil of <hi>Dignities,</hi> and murmur againſt our <hi>Betters;</hi> we <hi>Confederate</hi> and <hi>Aſſociate, Conſpire</hi> and <hi>Rebel, Murder</hi> Kings, and take poſſeſſion of their <hi>Thrones</hi> and <hi>Lands,</hi> and yet come off <hi>cleverly</hi> and with <hi>Applauſe,</hi> by putting all upon the ſcore of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Conſcience:</hi> And, being fortified with theſe <hi>Charms,</hi> there's nothing ſo <hi>Sacred</hi> that we dare not <hi>Prophane,</hi> nor ſo <hi>Horrid</hi> that we dare not <hi>do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doubtleſs the <hi>Papiſts</hi> firſt taught the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> this <hi>Religious Juggle:</hi> For they have all along conſecrated their Deviliſh Practices by theſe Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Names.</hi> The Church's <hi>intereſt</hi> is the centre of their <hi>Religion,</hi> and their <hi>Conſciences</hi> turn upon the ſame <hi>Pin:</hi> that every thing is <hi>Pious, Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> and <hi>Meritorious</hi> that makes for the <hi>Cauſe;</hi> and there's no ſin with <hi>them</hi> like <hi>ill-luck</hi> and <hi>miſcarriage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, the <hi>Work</hi> of <hi>this Day</hi> had been a <hi>Bleſſed Work;</hi> the <hi>Traitors, Saints;</hi> and the <hi>Day</hi> a <hi>Red
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93057:9"/> letter'd Holy Day,</hi> as long as ever the Date of the <hi>Roman Calendar</hi> had laſted, if things had but gone merrily on for a few hours longer, till the fatal <hi>Thunderclap</hi> had gone off, and ſtruck the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> dead at a Blow!</p>
            <p>And then for drawing in a <hi>Sacrament</hi> to ſerve a <hi>purpoſe,</hi> there are no <hi>Simeonites</hi> no <hi>Levites</hi> in the World like them. Have you not heard of an <hi>Emperor</hi> diſpatch'd with the <hi>Euchariſtical Cup?</hi> and of a certain Pope ſuſpected to have been ſo ſerved by the <hi>Conſecrated Hoſt?</hi> Nay do's not the Sacrament it ſelf in their Notion, <hi>fleſh</hi> them in Cruelty, and teach theſe common <hi>God-eaters,</hi> to devour, and ſuck the Blood of <hi>Men?</hi> The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Inſtance ſeems to whiſper ſomewhat like it: For the Conſpirators firſt <hi>hardned</hi> themſelves with the <hi>Tranſubſtantiated</hi> Elements, and then, like <hi>Judas,</hi> big with the Devil and Malice, went on boldly, as far as Gods providence would let them, with the <hi>Execution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. The laſt thing I ſhall obſerve in this Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy, is the <hi>concluding</hi> Act, their impartial cruelty in the <hi>Execution.</hi> The <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Prince,</hi> the <hi>People,</hi> all the <hi>Men</hi> of the City that were within the reach of their Fury, were offer'd up a <hi>Propitiation</hi> to their <hi>Revenge,</hi> for <hi>Shechem</hi>'s Folly: and all the <hi>Females</hi> ſeized on to make <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> for <hi>one ſingle
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93057:10"/> Dinah's</hi> Virginity. And the Hiſtories of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> will inform you, how the Papiſts there, like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> or the Wild <hi>Indians,</hi> have <hi>Run a Muc,</hi> and murder'd all that were not of the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Shiboleth</hi> and <hi>Complexion.</hi> But the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed of all their <hi>exploits</hi> that ever they did, or deſigned to do, was this <hi>Project</hi> of the <hi>Powder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plot:</hi> That they ſhould conſpire againſt a <hi>King,</hi> not their <hi>enemies</hi> but their <hi>Own;</hi> a <hi>King</hi> that ſtudied their <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> (and had like to have paid for it too;) a <hi>King</hi> of their own <hi>Religion,</hi> or of that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which they <hi>profeſs</hi> and ought to <hi>be,</hi> a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> and with him the <hi>Royal Branches,</hi> the hopes of the <hi>Succesſion;</hi> the <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>Judges</hi> of the Land, the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the Church, the <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> of the People, the <hi>Government,</hi> the <hi>Strength,</hi> the <hi>Religion</hi> of the Nation, to Confound them all in a <hi>Moment,</hi> that they might never <hi>ſee,</hi> nor live to <hi>ask</hi> who hurt them; This was the greateſt Maſter-piece of Treaſon, that ever the Reprobate Wit of Man projected. <hi>Curſed be their Anger, for it was fierce; and their Wrath, for it was cruel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We can make no better <hi>Application</hi> of this, than what <hi>Jacob</hi> did of the <hi>Treachery</hi> of his Sons, <hi>O my Soul come not thou into their ſecret; unto their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, mine Honour, be not thou united.</hi> Which is both
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93057:10"/> a <hi>Proteſtation</hi> againſt their Wicked Proceedings, and a <hi>Deſire</hi> that he might never be concerned in the <hi>like,</hi> and that what was <hi>paſt</hi> might not ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reflect upon his <hi>Honour,</hi> nor be charged unto his Account. And I believe we are willing to be thought, in reſpect of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> of the ſame mind that the Patriarch was in reſpect of his <hi>Sons.</hi> I ſuppoſe few of us are of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Clubs, or frequent <hi>Wild-houſe</hi> to Cap Treaſon at the <hi>Jeſuits Goſſipings. Popery</hi> is ſo juſtly Deteſtable among us, that we care not how little we have of the Company of ſuch as profeſs it. And it would be well if we were as irreconcileable to their <hi>Councels,</hi> as we are to their <hi>Perſons:</hi> and equally enemies to their <hi>Deſigns,</hi> as to their <hi>Religion.</hi> They can never hurt us, except we play <hi>booty,</hi> and help to do it our ſelves: Which <hi>They</hi> are ſo well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of, that they deſpair of our <hi>Ruin</hi> any other way: And the laſt <hi>Trick</hi> that with any hopes of a probable ſucceſs they can Play upon us, is to fit us for their own <hi>Turns,</hi> and wind us into the <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> againſt our ſelves. And that either by Poiſoning our <hi>Principles,</hi> or turning the edge of our <hi>Practices</hi> againſt one another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They have a deſign upon our <hi>Principles,</hi> and to make us the <hi>Hereticks</hi> they are pleaſed to <hi>call</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93057:11"/> us, and ſuch as they are Themſelves. For what they believe diſtinct from other Chriſtians, is commonly erroneous and dangerous. The Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernumerary Articles of the <hi>Trent</hi> Conventicle have almoſt every one a <hi>Plot</hi> in them, either to <hi>deſtroy</hi> others, or to <hi>advance</hi> themſelves. But their <hi>Politick</hi> Creed, which ſerves to keep up the State and Grandeur of <hi>Holy Church,</hi> is moſt <hi>fatally</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious; tending to the ſubverſion of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Monarchies in the world: The Articles whereof are ſuch as theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the King is the POPE's or the PEOPLE's Creature;</hi> for 'tis indifferent to their great <hi>Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels</hi> the Jeſuits, whoſe he be, ſo he do but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to either; Take him whole, or divide him, or how you pleaſe, ſo that God, to whom alone he belongs and is accountable, may have the leaſt ſhare in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the</hi> Pope <hi>if he be a</hi> Heretick, <hi>and the</hi> People <hi>of a</hi> Tyrant, <hi>may depoſe him:</hi> They being Judges whether he be ſo or no. That it is as much as his Crown is worth for either of them to call him ſo.<note place="margin">That is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing him a Heretick, or no friend to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Cath. Intereſt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But if the <hi>People</hi> contend to have him all to themſelves, the <hi>Jeſuit</hi>'s a fair chapman, and will rather give up the Spiritual intereſt of the <hi>Chair,</hi> than diſpute it: that if the People do but <hi>depoſe</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:93057:11"/> him, be it for <hi>Tyranny,</hi> be it for <hi>Hereſie,</hi> nay be it for <hi>Popery,</hi> or <hi>ſuſpicion</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> do but depoſe him, and he is contented.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Presbytery</hi> put in for a ſhare, and pretend an Intereſt in the <hi>Religious</hi> part of him, the Jeſuit will give them leave to Excommunicate him; to deliver him to Satan, to do any thing with him that may but <hi>leſſen</hi> him, and help to bring down his <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> to the <hi>Duſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay their Creed is ſo far for the <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty,</hi> or rather the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> that it gives you to believe, that if Kings miſmanage their <hi>Truſts,</hi> if they <hi>Traiterouſly</hi> invade the <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> of the Subjects, 'tis the peoples <hi>duty</hi> to call them to an account, to <hi>judge</hi> them if they know how to <hi>catch</hi> them; and if not, that then 'tis free for every man to <hi>kill</hi> them where he finds them; and that 'tis good <hi>State-Divinity</hi> to appoint <hi>Rewards</hi> for ſo doing, as well as for killing <hi>Bears</hi> and <hi>Wolves,</hi> and deſtroying the <hi>Vermine</hi> of the Country.</p>
            <p>Theſe Principles, howſoever they have been Tranſcribed by the <hi>Northern Evangeliſts,</hi> with the <hi>laſt horrid improvement,</hi> owe their firſt draught to the <hi>Jeſuit</hi>'s <hi>Pen.</hi> Theſe were Machinations forg'd for the ſubverſion of the Proteſtant Religion; by Mining its main Fort, the Civil Government,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93057:12"/> and lopping the Power of Kings, the <hi>Defenders of our Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to their ſhame be it ſpoken, there are too many <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> affectedly Fond of that Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, who are thus <hi>Jeſuited: Whoſe Souls are in their ſecret,</hi> who think their <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Councels,</hi> and are of their very <hi>Judgment,</hi> as if the ſame Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Genius, the <hi>Soul</hi> of a <hi>Traitor</hi> inſpired them <hi>both.</hi> And yet with what <hi>zeal</hi> do they declaim againſt <hi>Popery?</hi> with what <hi>Indignation</hi> and <hi>ſcorn</hi> do they expoſe the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and ſerve the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> upon them <hi>in Effigie</hi> at certain <hi>ſolemn</hi> Times? How do they Curſe the Helliſh Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy of this Day: and do all that <hi>Good Subjects</hi> ought to do and <hi>more,</hi> to ſignifie their <hi>Abhorrence</hi> of it? But for all this, <hi>Ye are Friends,</hi> Sirs, <hi>and why fall ye out?</hi> why, but becauſe ye <hi>envy</hi> their Plots, but becauſe ye are for a <hi>Monopoly,</hi> and ſpight any body to be Traitors like your ſelves.</p>
            <p>Lord! what <hi>haſte</hi> do they make from <hi>Rome,</hi> and what a <hi>diſtance</hi> do they keep in all things elſe? <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is voted <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> becauſe 'tis the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>that</hi> Church; and ſo it was of all the Churches in the world, before <hi>Popery</hi> was known, either <hi>Name</hi> or <hi>Thing.</hi> The <hi>Liturgy</hi> is cried down for a <hi>Maſs-book</hi> Tranſlated, becauſe 'tis a <hi>Form;</hi> and <hi>they</hi> chooſe rather to talk to God in <hi>extempore</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93057:12"/> blaſphemy, than addreſs themſelves in ſober words and ſence, if they be <hi>compoſed</hi> to their hands. <hi>Ceremony</hi> is all exploded upon this Account; and one party refuſe good manners to God, becauſe the other is <hi>Superſtitious.</hi> In moſt matters of mere <hi>Opinion,</hi> that are not of the very <hi>Eſſence</hi> of <hi>Faith;</hi> they endeavour to <hi>think</hi> as far from <hi>Papiſts</hi> as 'tis poſſible, and in ſome Points even to <hi>falſhood</hi> and <hi>abſurdity.</hi> Nay, they have much ado to believe their <hi>Creed</hi> for fear it ſhould be <hi>Popiſh:</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> ſcrue the Article of the <hi>Holy Catholick Church</hi> too tight, <hi>they</hi> either leave it out, or however ſeem as if they knew not what to make on't. And 'tis ſtrange that while they ſo <hi>induſtriouſly</hi> ſhun them in all things elſe, they ſhould thus concur in <hi>that</hi> which is moſt <hi>Abominable</hi> and <hi>wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of the moſt Moderate and Wiſeſt of the Papiſts, diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Court</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>renounce</hi> the Former, though they <hi>adhere</hi> to the latter: for however they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of their <hi>Religion,</hi> they can by no means diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with their <hi>Maxims</hi> of <hi>State:</hi> upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count whereof, the <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Jeſuites</hi> is as <hi>hateful</hi> and <hi>Obnoxious</hi> unto <hi>them,</hi> as it is to <hi>us;</hi> their curſed <hi>Principles</hi> going more againſt the <hi>grain</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> than all their Religious Fopperies
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93057:13"/> and Superſtitions. But who would think that men of delicate and demure <hi>Conſciences,</hi> ſhould be Papiſts in the worſt ſence? That they ſhould ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor <hi>Popery,</hi> and eſpouſe <hi>Jeſuitiſm?</hi> which is to ſwallow down the <hi>rank gob,</hi> and only nauſeate the <hi>Luſcious Kickſhaws.</hi> And ſuch are the Phanatick <hi>Antimonarchiſts</hi> of this Age; they are Papiſts, the worſt of Papiſts, Jeſuites <hi>in temporalibus,</hi> and if that be not a fine forwardneſs <hi>in Ordine ad Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualia,</hi> let the world judge.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Jeſuitiſm</hi> hath not only poiſon'd the <hi>Principles,</hi> and ſo faſcinated the Judgments of many Proteſtants, that they are of their <hi>Councel,</hi> and <hi>think Treaſon</hi> in common with <hi>them;</hi> But we are ſo bewitch'd as to be <hi>Papiſt's Inſtruments, Tools</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> and to contribute to the Management of their <hi>Plots</hi> againſt our ſelves; like <hi>Changelings,</hi> we ſuffer our ſelves to be <hi>practis'd</hi> upon, and conform our <hi>Actions</hi> to the Roguiſh <hi>ends</hi> that <hi>they</hi> direct them. <hi>They</hi> ſtudy to <hi>divide</hi> us, and we are <hi>divided; They</hi> Clap their hands, and we Quarrel; <hi>They</hi> ſhove at the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and we <hi>Rebel,</hi> and lend them a <hi>helping hand; They</hi> are Mining at the <hi>Foundation</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> and the hands of a <hi>Legion</hi> of Sects, are Pecking at her <hi>Outworks</hi> and <hi>Battlements;</hi> Finally,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93057:13"/> they <hi>Forecaſt</hi> the Miſchief, and we Blunder on to the <hi>Execution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for all this good Service, the Papiſts are beholden to their <hi>Phanatick Friends;</hi> thoſe truſty <hi>Jobbers,</hi> that never fail to do their Maſters at <hi>Rome</hi> a good <hi>turn,</hi> as far as <hi>Faction, Sedition, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion</hi> (the embroilment of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi>) will go. And yet, with a <hi>demure Impudence,</hi> they dare to brand their Proteſtant <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> with the character of <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Popiſhly affected;</hi> Terms more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly beſtowed at <hi>Home.</hi> Why? Do they fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent <hi>Maſs?</hi> Do they receive the Sacrament in <hi>one kind?</hi> Do they worſhip the <hi>Hoſt,</hi> bow down to <hi>Images,</hi> or pray to <hi>Saints;</hi> and all this in a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage as little underſtood by <hi>themſelves</hi> as by the <hi>Roman Idols?</hi> Do they tear their <hi>Bibles</hi> for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing their <hi>Errors,</hi> or lay them aſide to make way for <hi>Tradition?</hi> Do they pin their Faith upon the <hi>Pope's Infallibility,</hi> and make the <hi>Vicar</hi> as great a <hi>God</hi> as his <hi>Lord?</hi> Is <hi>Purgatory one Article</hi> of their <hi>Creed,</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> another? Do they go to the <hi>Mart</hi> for <hi>Pardons</hi> and <hi>Indulgences,</hi> take <hi>Leaſes</hi> of their <hi>ſins</hi> for <hi>Term of Life,</hi> and hire the <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Supernumerary Merits</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> to Bribe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to receive them when they are <hi>Dead?</hi> Nay, is not their <hi>Doctrine</hi> as <hi>Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtolical</hi> as the <hi>Creed,</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93057:14"/> their <hi>Worſhip pure;</hi> reformed not only from the <hi>Groſs</hi> Superſtitions of <hi>Popiſh Paganiſm,</hi> but from thoſe <hi>Tollerabiles ineptiae,</hi> that our Bleſſed <hi>Reformers</hi> (Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs afterward) in <hi>K. Ed.</hi> 6. his days, were forced to diſpenſe with; and yet ſcorned the Name of <hi>Papiſts</hi> as <hi>much,</hi> and deſerved it as <hi>little,</hi> as our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>Sticklers?</hi> Where's the <hi>Popery</hi> then, is it in their <hi>Religion,</hi> or in their <hi>Morals?</hi> Are they <hi>Papiſts</hi> becauſe they are <hi>Loyal</hi> to their Prince, and <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> to his Laws; and, to their eternal Honour be it ſpoken, were never juſtly Attainted for being <hi>otherwiſe?</hi> Is it <hi>Popery</hi> to Aſſert the Government againſt Politick <hi>Innovators,</hi> and to ſtand up for the <hi>Divine prerogative</hi> of diſpoſing <hi>Thrones</hi> and <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,</hi> that it may be kept Inviolate? Are they <hi>Papiſts</hi> becauſe they are <hi>tender</hi> of their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and dare not ſuffer them to be over-ruled by <hi>Civil prudentials,</hi> and <hi>Reaſons of State?</hi> becauſe they will not give their <hi>Voices</hi> againſt the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> nor conſent that they ſhould be ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeded by the <hi>Arbitrary Dictates</hi> of <hi>Machiavillians</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts?</hi> becauſe they will not forfeit their <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity</hi> to keep out <hi>Popery,</hi> nor go to <hi>Hell</hi> to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal an <hi>Inquiſition?</hi> If this be <hi>Popery,</hi> may the Loyal Sons of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> be ſuch <hi>Papiſts</hi> ever.</p>
            <p>But are they <hi>Papiſts</hi> indeed? why then, <hi>Satans Kingdom is divided againſt it ſelf.</hi> For with whom
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93057:14"/> do Papiſts <hi>diſpute?</hi> at whom do they <hi>rail?</hi> againſt whom do they <hi>Conſpire,</hi> but the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the moſt impregnable <hi>Fort</hi> in the world againſt them? Alas! our petty <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Factions</hi> are our <hi>Weakneſſes,</hi> and the Champions of <hi>Rome</hi> are ſo far from Levelling their Artillery againſt <hi>them,</hi> that they <hi>connive</hi> at them, they <hi>indulge</hi> them, they make them <hi>more,</hi> in hopes to enter at them, one day, as through <hi>Breaches;</hi> ſuch <hi>poor</hi> defences are they againſt the <hi>Roman Adverſary.</hi> But they that are ſo forward to fix the <hi>Papiſt</hi> upon <hi>others,</hi> ought certainly to conſider how eaſily it may be returned upon <hi>themſelves:</hi> Though it is the trick of ſome Artiſts at <hi>Law,</hi> to make themſelves <hi>Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffs</hi> when their Cauſe is <hi>naught.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not <hi>Catechiſe</hi> them out of the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Romiſh Creed;</hi> but only ask them what they ſay to their refuſal of <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> ſuch as were particularly intended for the proof of <hi>Loyal Proteſtants,</hi> and the Detection of <hi>Romiſh Bigots?</hi> What ſay <hi>they</hi> for themſelves that take them with <hi>private</hi> and <hi>equivocal Reſtrictions,</hi> which <hi>Papiſts</hi> might do as well as <hi>they?</hi> What do they anſwer to their communicating with the Church in her <hi>Service</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and receiving the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> according to the <hi>Eſtabliſhed form</hi> and <hi>Rites,</hi> upon <hi>extraordinary</hi> occaſions to ſerve a <hi>Turn;</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93057:15"/> then excuſing their <hi>Diſobedience,</hi> with a Pretence of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> at all <hi>other times,</hi> when neither their <hi>own,</hi> nor the <hi>Intereſts</hi> of the <hi>Faction</hi> do oblige them?</p>
            <p>But to compound the buſineſs once for all: Let them draw any tolerable <hi>Scheme</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> with all its material <hi>Diſcriminations</hi> from the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chriſtianity,</hi> and if any part of it prove a <hi>Mark</hi> upon the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and if, in the main, it do not <hi>blacken</hi> the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from it ten times more, I dare be bold to ſay we may yield the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and give them leave to call us as many <hi>Papiſts</hi> as they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>But who ſees not what eminent <hi>ſervice</hi> is done to the <hi>Roman intereſt,</hi> by this foul <hi>Aſperſion?</hi> that any thing, but <hi>Mere Charity,</hi> would ſuſpect them to be <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> or <hi>Penſioners</hi> for their pains. For is not this the way to bring <hi>Popery</hi> into <hi>Reputation,</hi> by making it the Character of ſo many <hi>Pious, Learned,</hi> and <hi>Loyal</hi> Men, who indeed abhor it; and cannot demonſtrate that they do ſo, better, than by <hi>ſerving</hi> God in the <hi>Reformed, Eſtabliſh'd</hi> Way? Will it not enhance the price of their <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Superſtitions,</hi> to give it out to the World that the moſt <hi>Judicious</hi> and <hi>knowing</hi> men in it, have a good <hi>Opinion</hi> and think <hi>well</hi> of them? Is not this a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble expedient to put a creditable <hi>Gloſs</hi> upon a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93057:15"/> piece of <hi>Jeſuitiſm,</hi> by perſwading people that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England-worthies equivocate</hi> and <hi>diſſemble;</hi> and whatſoever they <hi>Write,</hi> whatſoever they <hi>ſay,</hi> whatſoever they <hi>proteſt</hi> and <hi>ſwear</hi> to the contrary, yet that they are <hi>Papiſts</hi> at the Root? and thus by foiſting in the <hi>forged</hi> Authority of ſo many <hi>great</hi> and <hi>gallant</hi> men, they teach others to <hi>Lye, Diſſemble</hi> and <hi>Forſwear</hi> themſelves in things of the <hi>greateſt moment,</hi> and warrant them ſo to do, by the pretence of the moſt <hi>Authentick precedents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, they cannot but know what Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage an <hi>overſized Computation</hi> gives to a Party; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis a Trick of their <hi>own,</hi> and every day practized; to boaſt of Numbers to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves look <hi>Formidable</hi> and their enemies <hi>little.</hi> And does it not make the hearts of the people <hi>ſhrink,</hi> and their heads <hi>hang down,</hi> and their hands grow <hi>feeble,</hi> to hear of <hi>French Armies, Spaniſh Pilgrims, Black bills, Iriſh Ruffians, Domeſtick Cut-throats,</hi> and that over and above, the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England-men</hi> are <hi>Papiſts.</hi> and will Treacherouſly ſurrender both <hi>Themſelves</hi> and the <hi>Cauſe</hi> upon the firſt <hi>Parley?</hi> What a mighty encouragement would this be to the <hi>Romiſh Faction,</hi> to conſider that they have the <hi>Governours</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> the <hi>Court,</hi> the <hi>Nobility,</hi> the <hi>Gentry,</hi> and a great liſt of the <hi>Commonalty</hi> too on their ſide? (for all that are
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93057:16"/> Loyal to the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> have the <hi>Brand</hi> upon them) and that nothing remains un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conquered but a few <hi>divided ſcatterings;</hi> how, I ſay, would the Conceit of ſuch an <hi>Intereſt</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolden them to attempt their long-intended wickedneſs, of <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Slaughter;</hi> But that they know us <hi>better</hi> than to <hi>Truſt</hi> us, in ſpight of any thing that the <hi>Malicious</hi> Rhetorick of our <hi>Foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth'd Incendiaries</hi> can perſwade them to?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, This is as probable a way as could be thought on to palliate the <hi>Odium</hi> of that Religion; to conclude <hi>Popery</hi> under the Notion of <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency,</hi> and to harden the World into a <hi>Belief</hi> that there's no ſuch <hi>danger</hi> in it as was <hi>ſuſpected:</hi> Will not bandying it about at this wild rate be the way to loſe it? and will not the <hi>formidableneſs</hi> of it wear off by ſuch <hi>frequent</hi> and <hi>familiar</hi> handling? I am ſure that <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Phanaticiſm</hi> have a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Kindred</hi> that hath met with this Courteous Fortune, to be diſcounted from the Catalogue of ſins, by ſome of its <hi>Friends,</hi> for no other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but the <hi>looſe</hi> and <hi>Impertinent</hi> Application of it; and <hi>that,</hi> by Name, is <hi>Schiſm.</hi> For thus 'tis argued by a <hi>Doughty Advocate: The Church of</hi>
               <note place="margin">J. O. Plea for Non-Con.</note> Rome <hi>call the Greek Church Schiſmatick, and the Greek Church return the Schiſmatick upon the Church of</hi> Rome: <hi>the Church of</hi> England <hi>make the</hi> Romiſh
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93057:16"/> 
               <hi>Church the Schiſmatick, and the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>charge the Schiſm upon the Church of</hi> England: <hi>Again, the Church of</hi> England <hi>calls her</hi> Diſſenters <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, and the</hi> Diſſenters <hi>think the Church to be Schiſmaticks from them: and ſo we have called one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Schiſmaticks round;</hi> and then he infers, <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Schiſm is but</hi> Vox, &amp; praeterea nihil, <hi>nothing but a meer noiſe and Nickname which every Party caſts upon all them who are not of their Society.</hi> Thus this horrid ſin, which the Church for many hundred years accounted <hi>Damnable,</hi> is, by the <hi>petulant</hi> uſe of the Word upon <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>unjuſt</hi> occaſions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>irivial</hi> and <hi>indifferent</hi> thing. And what elſe do you think, will be the effect of making the Charge of Popery ſo <hi>common,</hi> eſpecially where it is ſo <hi>falſly</hi> and <hi>abuſively</hi> applied?</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what a <hi>Confederacy</hi> there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> and a <hi>Fanatick</hi> Spirit; and how the Popiſh Intrigues againſt the Church and Government are <hi>carried</hi> on, and moſt likely to be <hi>perfected</hi> (if at all) by a Faction, miſcalled a <hi>True Proteſtant</hi> party, amongſt our ſelves. And I am perſwaded that the moſt <hi>Rational</hi> fears of <hi>Popery</hi> at this day are ſuch as the <hi>Multiform Fanaticiſm</hi> of this Age, hath rouz'd and conjur'd up in the minds of <hi>ſober, thinking</hi> men.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:93057:17"/>
            <p>And here I muſt <hi>out-run</hi> the Text, to <hi>purſue</hi> the <hi>Traitor</hi> a little farther. 'Twas <hi>Jacob</hi>'s deſire, that as his <hi>Soul</hi> was unſpotted, ſo his <hi>Honour</hi> might never be ſtained with the <hi>Sichemites</hi> blood; and doubtleſs he had his <hi>wiſh:</hi> For <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> were ſuch <hi>puiſny Traitors</hi> as to confeſs the <hi>Fact,</hi> and take the <hi>Guilt</hi> upon themſelves. But the crafty <hi>Brotherhood</hi> have a Reach beyond them: They do the <hi>Deed,</hi> and lay the <hi>Brat</hi> at their Father's door: They aſſert the Treacherous <hi>Principles,</hi> and puſh on the <hi>Deſigns</hi> and <hi>Intereſts</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Faction; and to clear themſelves, Paſquil their Royal and Ghoſtly Parents, with the infamous name of <hi>Papiſt,</hi> as if it were an <hi>Indelible Character</hi> upon the Engliſh Monarchy and Hierarchy.</p>
            <p>And indeed all the notorious Villanies they have from time to time been guilty of, have ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more been thus ſhamm'd upon the Patriarch's ſcore. When they Conſpire againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment (O monſtrous Soleciſm!) the King is proclaim'd the <hi>Traitor:</hi> when they <hi>rebel,</hi> and make the Land <hi>drunk</hi> with its own Blood, who's the <hi>Murderer</hi> but <hi>He?</hi> When they uſurp an <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary jurisdiction</hi> over the Perſons, Lives and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of their Fellow Subjects to <hi>plunder, ſequeſter,</hi> and <hi>kill</hi> at their Pleaſure, who's the <hi>Tyrant</hi> but the <hi>King?</hi> he is <hi>Apprehended, Arraigned, Sentenc'd,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93057:17"/> Murdered</hi> for thoſe very <hi>Crimes</hi> that they commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And who can reflect ſoberly upon theſe things, and not <hi>bleſs</hi> himſelf with <hi>Jacob,</hi> in the Text, <hi>O my ſoul, come not thou into their ſecret; unto their Aſſembly, mine Honour, be not thou united?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Conclude: You all pretend an irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable <hi>Averſion</hi> to <hi>Popery,</hi> and I believe you <hi>hate it.</hi> For ſhame then ſcorn to be <hi>Trepan'd</hi> and <hi>led away</hi> by that <hi>deteſted</hi> Faction. Your <hi>Honour's</hi> at ſtake, and it you have any ſparks of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch's <hi>Heroiſm,</hi> make a generous <hi>proteſt</hi> againſt Popery and all its Intereſts; ſuffer not your ſelves to be drawn into the ſervice of the Party <hi>blindly,</hi> to work their wretched ends, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the <hi>ſordid</hi> and <hi>diſgraceful wickedneſs</hi> for them. Are you not aſhamed to be <hi>Bubbled</hi> out of the Reputation of <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Underſtanding</hi> men; and to be ranked in the Notion of <hi>Tools</hi> and <hi>Cullies?</hi> Are you not aſhamed to be ſubject to the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Nod</hi> of the men you <hi>hate,</hi> and to <hi>ſlave</hi> and <hi>foul</hi> your <hi>fingers</hi> in their <hi>dirty drudgery?</hi> There's not a <hi>Faction</hi> among us but is in <hi>Vaſſalage</hi> unto <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſerves the Pope with a <hi>blind Obedience;</hi> our <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> are all managed by <hi>Popiſh Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> and <hi>Conduct:</hi> and the <hi>Wooden horſe</hi> with a belly full of <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Treaſons,</hi> is a burden prepared for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93057:18"/> the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> ſhoulders; They ſhall have the <hi>Pains,</hi> the <hi>Shame,</hi> and the <hi>Hazard;</hi> while Papiſts look <hi>on,</hi> and only wait the <hi>ſucceſs,</hi> that they may ſieze the <hi>Prize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore for the ſake of our <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> for the ſake of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and for our own <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi>'s ſake, let us <hi>abjure</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and Phanaticiſm at once: Let us <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Obey the King,</hi> and <hi>Renounce</hi> all <hi>Traiterous</hi> and <hi>Diſloyal</hi> Principles; Let us reſolutely adhere to the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>keep the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace;</hi> and ſo <hi>cheat</hi> our Adverſaries of thoſe Advantages, that they both <hi>Seek</hi> and <hi>Reap</hi> by our <hi>Diviſions:</hi> Let us not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the <hi>Church,</hi> with the <hi>undeſerved</hi> Character of <hi>Popiſh</hi> or <hi>Popiſhly</hi> affected, and thereby <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate</hi> the Curſed <hi>Appellation;</hi> but (aſcribing it where 'tis only due) let it carry its deſerved <hi>Odium</hi> along with it, as long as <hi>Popery</hi> has either <hi>Being</hi> or <hi>Remembrance</hi> in the World: Let us pray for the Grace of God, that <hi>our Souls may never be of their ſecret;</hi> and by living <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Vertuous</hi> lives in all <hi>Godlineſs</hi> and <hi>Honeſty,</hi> engage the Divine Protection on our <hi>ſide,</hi> that, <hi>unto their Aſſemblies</hi> we <hi>may never be united.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:93057:18"/>
            <p>Finally, to expreſs our <hi>Abhorrence</hi> the more <hi>Emphatically,</hi> why may we not take up the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch's Imprecation;</hi> ſince it is ſo <hi>Modeſt</hi> a <hi>Curſe,</hi> not of the <hi>Men,</hi> but of their <hi>Inhumanity?</hi> What <hi>Devout</hi> Son of the <hi>Church?</hi> what <hi>Loyal</hi> Subject of the <hi>Government,</hi> can hold his <hi>Indignation</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to ſay, <hi>Curſed</hi> be all <hi>Jeſuitiſm,</hi> whether it be the Spawn of <hi>Tybur</hi> or the <hi>Tweed; Curſed</hi> be all <hi>Clandeſtine, underground Treaſon,</hi> and <hi>bare-fac'd above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board Rebellion; Curſed</hi> be <hi>Popiſh-Plots,</hi> and <hi>Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Aſſociations: Curſed be their Anger, for it is fierce; and their wrath, for it is cruel?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Bleſſed,</hi> for ever Bleſſed, <hi>be the Lord who hath not given us over as a prey unto their Teeth.</hi> That <hi>our ſoul is eſcaped as a Bird out of the ſnare of the Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, the ſnare is broken and we are eſcaped. Our help is in the Name of the Lord who made Heaven and Earth;</hi> To whom be Glory, <hi>&amp;c. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
